A Guide to the Stephen S. Sharp Papers 1969-1980
Lewis F. Powell, Jr. Archives, Washington and Lee University
Lewis F. Powell, Jr. Archives, School of Law, Washington and Lee University
Stephen A. Sharp Papers 1969-1980
Lewis F. Powell, Jr. Archives, School of Law, Washington and Lee University
007
46 cu. ft.
Dunn Campaign and Impeachment portions of these papers were placed on permanent loan at Washington and Lee University Library Special Collections by Stephen A. Sharp in December 1974. There is no record of when the FCC papers arrived there. Because the impeachment inquiry papers in the Sharp papers complement those in the M. Caldwell Butler papers, the Sharp collection was transferred to the Powell Archives in the Washington and Lee University School of Law in March 1993. This was done with the permission of the brother of the lender, Matthew T. Sharp, who held the power-of-attorney for Stephen Sharp.
Administrative Information
Access
There are not restrictions on access.
Biographical/Historical Information
Stephen A. Sharp was born in Columbus, Ohio and raised in Wooster, Ohio. He received his B.A. degree from Washington and Lee University in 1969, and his J.D. degree from the University of Virginia in 1973.
Sharp took a leave of absence from law school to serve as communications director of the 1970 Tennessee gubernatorial campaign of Winfield Dunn. He went on to serve temporarily as news secretary and special assistant to the Governor-elect before returning to law school.
He joined the Federal Communications Commission (FCC) in 1972 in the Office of the General Counsel, and ultimately served in every division of that office. He resigned from the Commission in January 1974 to serve as counsel to the Impeachment Inquiry of the Committee on the Judiciary of the U.S. House of Representatives.
Sharp returned to the Commission at the end of the inquiry, and in January 1975 moved to the Litigation Division, representing the FCC in appellate litigation in the U.S. Circuit Courts of Appeals and the Supreme Court. At that time he also served as the chief advisor to the General Counsel concerning political broadcasting and the fairness doctrine. In September 1976, he moved to the office of FCC Commissioner Margita E. White as legal assistant.
He resigned from the Commission in December 1978 to become associated with the law firm of Schnader, Harrison, Segal & Lewis in its Washington office. In 1981, Sharp returned to the FCC as General Counsel. In 1982, President Ronald Reagan nominated Sharp to be an FCC Commissioner, a position he held until 1983. In August 1983, he joined the law firm of Skadden, Arps, Slate, Meagher and Flom in order to establish a telecommunications group within the firm. He was later of counsel to the law firm of Patton, Boggs & Blow while serving as President of Spectrum Consumer Products Company of Alexandria, Virginia.
Scope and Content Information
These papers document three specific aspects of the career of Stephen A. Sharp: 1) His work as communications director for the 1970 campaign to re-elect Winfield Dunn as governor of Tennessee; 2) His service as Associate Minority Counsel to the House Judiciary Committee 1974 Presidential Impeachment Inquiry; and 3) His work as the chief advisor to the Federal Communications Commission General Counsel concerning political broadcasting and the fairness doctrine, 1976-1980.
Winfield Dunn campaign papers, 4.5 cu.ft., include: public opinion polling research; releases; notes; daily campaign schedules; and press clippings. Also included are 7 audio cassette recordings of interviews with: Winfield Dunn, John J. Hooker, Jr., Bill Jenkins, Jack McNeil, Claude Robertson, and Stanley T.Snodgrass.
The U.S. House Judiciary Committee Impeachment Inquiry, 36.5 cu.ft., papers deal mainly with investigations of Richard M. Nixon Presidential campaign financing, and the role of Herbert Kalmbach in these activities. Materials include: committee research materials arranged in numbered ring binders; minority counsel internal memoranda; and printed Congressional reports and documents. Some processing has been done in this subgroup. A detailed listing of folder and publication titles is included in the container list. The materials are listed and housed in the order in which they were received. Certain overarching delineations appear including: Kalmbach and Campaign Financing, Materials re Kalmbach, Campaign Financing Materials and Sharp Notebooks.
The Federal Communications Commission papers, 5 cu. ft., deal almost exclusively with the application of the Fairness Doctrine by television networks during the 1976 elections. Materials include: Legislative histories and other research materials about the fairness doctrine; complaints and pleadings of candidates and organizations; and Sharp memos, notes and research materials from his work in response to these complaints.
Contents List
- Winfield Dunn for Governor of Tennessee Campaign 1969-1971
  - Uninventoried papers (Carton 1-4)
  - Oral History Audio Cassettes c. 1971 (Box 5)
    - Winfield Dunn
    - John J. Hooker Jr.
    - Bill Jenkins
    - Jack McNeil
    - Claude Robertson
    - Stanley T. Snodgrass
- House Judiciary Committee Nixon Impeachment Inquiry 1974
  - Published Materials 1972-1974
    - United States Senate Select Committee Hearings, Printed and bound materials (Carton 6)
    - Presidential Campaign Activities of 1972, Books 1-15 & 21; Appendix; Draft of Final Report, Parts 1-3 (Carton 6-7)
    - United States Senate Committee on the Judiciary, Nomination of Elliot L. Richardson as Special Prosecutor, Parts 1 & 2 (Carton 8)
    - United States House of Representatives Committee on the Judiciary
      - Special Prosecutor and Watergate Grand Jury Legislation (Carton 8)
      - Constitutional Grounds for Presidential Impeachment (Carton 8)
      - Submission of Recorded Presidential Conversations (Carton 8)
      - Statement of Information Books I-X (Carton 8-9)
    - United States House of Representatives Report of Proceedings on Hearings held before Committee on the Judiciary, Impeachment Inquiry: Stenographic Minutes July 2, 1974 - July 30, 1974 (Carton 11)
    - Executive Privilege: A Constitutional Myth Raoul Berger (Carton 12)
    - The Offenses of Richard M. Nixon: a Guide for the People of the United States William Dobrovir (Carton 12)
    - Kentucky Primary and General Election, 1971 (Carton 12)
    - The Watergate Hearings: Break-in and Cover-up New York Times (Carton 12)
  - Personal and Procedural Notebooks
    - Impeachment Inquiry Minority Staff (Carton 13)
      "Staff Info & AP Task Force"
    - Logbooks February-August, 1974 (Carton 13)
  - Memoranda
    - Adverse Inference from Failure to Produce (Carton 13)
    - Immunity (Carton 13)
    - Sobpoena Procedure (Carton 13)
    - Enforcement of Committee Subpoenas (Carton 13)
    - Arrest Under Warrant (Carton 13)
    - Resisting Legislative Subpoenas Through Judicial Intervention (Carton 13)
    - Editorial Group (Carton 13)
    - Campaign Contributions (Mithchell & Stans) (Carton 13)
    - Burglary of Democratic Headquarters (Carton 13)
    - Internal and Procedural Feb. - Aug., 1974 & univentoried (Carton 13-14)
  - Herbert Kalmbach Investigation Materials
    - Kalmbach and Campaign Financing (Carton 15)
    - Kalmbach General Subject Files (Carton 15-16)
    - Interviews, Testimony, and Diaries 1969-1974 (Carton 17)
    - Judiciary Cross Reference Reports (Carton 19-24)
    - Miscellaneous Information re Kalmbach (Carton 25)
  - Campaign Finance Materials
    - Subject Files (Carton 26-36)
    - Indexed Statements Before the Judiciary Committee April 23, 1974 - May 25, 1974 (Carton 37-41)
    - "Miscellaneous Subject Files" (Carton 42)
    - Notebooks (Carton 43-45)
    - Reports and Memoranda re Presidential Tapes (Carton 46)
    - Miscellaneous, Duplicate, and Uninventoried Materials (Carton 47-50)
- Federal Communications Commission 1976-1980 (Carton 51-55)
  Uninventoried materials re the FCC and the Fairness Doctrine